Finding Aid for the Griffith Family Papers, 1845-1973
UCLA Library, Department of Special Collections
Griffith Family Papers,
1845-1973
2060
Griffith family
117 boxes (58.5 linear ft.) 1 oversize box
Griffith Jenkins Griffith (1850-1919) engaged in mining operations in Mexico. In 1882, he purchased Los Feliz Rancho near Los Angeles, and acquired extensive real estate in the city. In 1896, he donated most of his ranch to the city for a public park, and in 1912 provided money for the construction of an astronomical observatory on Mt. Hollywood. His son, Van Griffith, became president of the Los Angeles Park Board, and was manager of the Griffith Park Transportation Company. He was also a member of the Los Angeles Police Commission and an ombudsman for Mayor Fletcher Bowron. His wife, Constance Griffith, served on the Los Angeles board of directors of the League of Women Voters and on the state board. The collection contains manuscripts, documents, photographs, glass negatives, newspapers, maps, clippings, magazines, books, and miscellaneous memorabilia of the Griffith family, including Griffith J. Griffith, his son Van, and Van's wife, Constance Griffith, including material in the Citizens Research Institute, the Los Angeles city police commission, the Griffith Trust Fund, and the League of Women Voters.
University of California, Los Angeles. Library. Department of Special Collections. Los Angeles, California 90095-1575
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Advance notice required for access.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Van Griffith, 1975.
Gift of Mrs. Harold Griffith, 1976.
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Harold Griffith, 1976-77.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 4233097
Biography
Griffith Jenkins Griffith was born on January 4, 1850 in Glamorganshire, South Wales; attended Fowler Institute, New York City; came to California in 1873; engaged in mining operations in Mexico; in 1882 purchased Los Feliz Rancho near Los Angeles, and acquired extensive real estate in the city; in 1896 donated most of his ranch to the city for a public park, and in 1912 provided money for the construction of an astronomical observatory on Mt. Hollywood; died on July 6, 1919; his son, Van Griffith, became president of the Los Angeles Park Board, and was manager of the Griffith Park Transportation Company; he was also a member of the Los Angeles Police Commission and an ombudsman for Mayor Fletcher Bowron; his wife, Constance Griffith, served on the Los Angeles board of directors of the League of Women Voters and on the state board.
Scope and Content
Collection contains manuscripts, documents, photographs, glass negatives, newspapers, maps, clippings, magazines, books, and miscellaneous memorabilia of the Griffith family, including Griffith J. Griffith, founder of Griffith Park in Los Angeles. Also contains papers of his son Van, and Van's wife, Constance Griffith, including material in the Citizens Research Institute, the Los Angeles city police commission, the Griffith Trust Fund, and the League of Women Voters.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Griffith family--Archives.; Griffith, Griffith J.--Archives.; Griffith, Van--Archives.; Griffith, Constance--Archives.; Civic leaders--California--Los Angeles--Archival resources.
Container List
- Papers Relating to Aviation, [1910-1932]
  - Aero Club of California, [1910-1913]
    - 2 minute books, June 7, 1910-June 7, 1913. (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
      Includes:
      By-laws, 1909, 1911.
      Articles of Incorporation, April 2, 1910.
      Termination of affiliation with Aero Club of America, July 14, 1916.
    - Correspondence bills, membership applications, and miscellany, 1909-1913. (Box 1, Folder 3-14)
    - Correspondence bills, membership applications, and miscellany, 1909-1913. (Box 2, Folder 1-17)
    - Local aviation meetings of 1910, 1911-1912, and 1913. (Box 2, Folder 18-21)
    - Scrapbook of clippings re local aviation meets, 1912-1913. (Box 30)
    - Framed Certification of Articles of Incorporation of Aero Club of California, 1910. (Box 29)
  - Aviation Magazine and Griffith Aviation Field, [1909-1963]
    - 3 alphabetized book folders re Aviation Publishing Company and Griffith Aviation Field. (Box 3, Folder 2-18, Box 4)
      Includes correspondence, bills, photographs and biographical notes re flyers, 1909-15.
    - Clippings and correspondence re aviation and Griffith Aviation Park, 1912., (In envelope) (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Framed photograph of aviator Frank Champion. (Box 29)
    - 171 copper plates for photographs published in Aviation magazine. (Box 29)
    - Correspondence with Harold E. Morehouse, 1962-1963, and various items as listed on the folder. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Books, [1910-1932]
    - Yearbooks. Aero Club of America, 1910, 1911, 1913-1916. (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
    - Handbook. Aero Club of America, 1911. (Box 5, Folder 3)
      Advance copy and another copy.
    - Hoagland, Roland, W., ed. The Blue Book of Aviation. Los Angeles: The Hoagland Company, 1932. (Box 6)
    - Lougheed, Victor. Vehicles of the Air (3rd edition). Chicago: Reilly and Britton Company, 1911. (Box 6)
    - Hubbard, T.O'B., and others. The Aeroplane. London: Longmans, Green & Company, 1911. (Box 6)
    - An account of the exercises on the occasion of the presentation of the Langley Medal... May 6, 1913... Washington, D.C.: the Smithsonian Institution, 1913. (Box 6)
    - Langley, S.P. and Manley, Charles M. Langley memoir on mechanical flight. Washington, D.C.: the Smithsonian Institution, 1911. (Box 6)
    - Berrman, A.E. Aviation. London: Methuen & Company, & New York: G.H. Doran Company, 1913. (Box 7)
    - National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics. First and second annual reports (1915-1916). Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1916 & 1917. (Box 7)
    - National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics. Report no.13, Meteorology & Aeronautics. Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1917. (Box 7)
    - National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics. Report no.14, Experimental Research on Air Propellers. Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1917. (Box 7)
    - Hatfield, D.D. Aeroplane Scrapbook, 1911-1929. Northrup Institute of Technology, 1971. (Box 7)
    - 8 miscellaneous publications of the U.S. Geological Survey. (Box 8)
    - 10 miscellaneous brochures and pamphlets. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Magazines, [1910-1930]
    - Aviation (January-November 1911). Los Angeles, Aviation Publishing Company. (Box 3, Folder 1)
      vol.1, no.1-11.
    - Aeronautics (January-September and November-December 1909; January-October and December 1910; April-December 1911; January-March, July and September-November 1912; May-December 1913; January-October 1914; March-July 1915). New York: Aeronautics Press, Incorporated. (Box 9)
      vol.4, no.1-5.
      vol.5, no.1-3, 5-6.
      vol.6, no.1-6.
      vol.7, no.1-4, 6.
      vol.8, no.4-6.
      vol.9, no.1-6.
      vol.10, no.1-3.
      vol.11, no.1, 3-5.
      vol.12, no.5, 6.
      vol.13, no.1-6.
      vol.14, no.1-12.
      vol.15, no.1-8.
      vol.16, no.1-6, 8.
      vol.17, no.1-2.
    - Aerial Age (May-July 1913). Chicago: Aerial Age Publishing Company, Incorporated. (Box 10-11)
      vol.1, no.10.
      vol.2, no.1-2.
    - Aerial Age (March 22, May 10, 24, 31, June 28, July 5 and 19, September 13 and 27, October 18, 1915; January 18, April 24, May 15 and 29, July 10 and 24, September 25, October 9-30, November 13, December 18-25, 1916; January 1, 22-29, February 12, April 2 and 23, May 14 and 28, July 23, August 6, September 3, 1917). New York: Aerial Age Company, Incorporated. (Box 11)
      vol.1, no.1-8, 10, 11, 15, 16, 18-26.
      vol.2, no.2-5, 18-26.
      vol.3, no.1-6, 9, 11-17, 19-26.
      vol.4, no.1-2, 4-7, 9, 14-16, 19, 20, 22-26.
      vol.5, no.1-3, 6-9, 11-19, 21-25.
    - Aircraft (March-September, December 1911; January 1912). New York: the Lawson Publishing Company. (Box 11)
      vol.2, no.1-7, 10, 11.
    - Aero (December 10, 1910; October 21, November 11, 18, 1911). St. Louis: Aero Publishing Company. (Box 11)
      vol.3, no.3, 6, 7.
    - Flight (June 17, 1911). London: the Royal Aero Club of the United Kingdom. (Box 11)
      vol.3, no.24.
    - Flying (November 1912-December 1913; January-December 1914; January-June, August-October 1915; February-April, June-September 1916). New York: the Aero Club of America. (Box 12)
      vol.1, no.10-12.
      vol.2, no.1-12.
      vol.3, no.1-12.
      vol.4, no.1-5, 7-9.
      vol.5, no.1-3, 5-8.
    - Aero Club of America Bulletin (February/March, April 1912). New York: the Aero Club of America. (Box 13, Folder 1)
      vol.1, no.2,3.
    - Fly (December 1910; October-December 1911; January, March-April, June, August, September, November, December, 1912; April 1913). Philadelphia: Aero Publishing Company. (Box 13, Folder 2-4)
      vol.3, no.2, 12.
      vol.4, no.1-3, 5, 6, 8, 10, 11.
      vol.5, no.1-2, 6.
    - The Ace (April-July, 1922). Los Angeles: the Ace Publishing Company. (Box 13, Folder 5)
      vol.3,nos. 4-7.
    - Western Flight (June 14-28, 1913). San Francisco: Irvin C. Keeler. (Box 13, Folder 6)
      vol.1, no.1-3.
    - Aviation and Aeronautical Engineering (September 15, 1916). New York: the Gardner, Moffat Company. (Box 13, Folder 7)
      vol.1, no.4.
    - Aviation (July 5, 1930). New York: McGraw Hill Publishing Company, Incorporated. (Box 13, Folder 8)
      vol.29, no.1.
  - Duplicate Magazines, [1911-1930]
    - Aerial Age (June 1913). (Box 14)
      vol.2, no.1.
    - Aerial Age (August 2, October 11, 1915; March, 20, April 3, 1916). (Box 14)
      vol.1, no.20.
      vol.2, no.4.
      vol.3, no.1, 3.
    - Aeronautics (May-July 1911; December 1913). (Box 14)
      vol.8, no.5, 6.
      vol.9, no.1.
      vol.13, no.6.
    - Aero Club of America Bulletin (February/March, April 1912). (Box 14)
      vol.1, no.2 (2 copies), 3 (5 copies).
    - Aviation (July 5, 1930). (Box 14)
    - Flying (November 1912; November 1913; March-April 1914). (Box 14)
      vol.2, no.10 (2 copies).
      vol.3, no.2-3.
    - Western Flight (June 21, 1913). (Box 14)
      vol.1, no.2.
- Papers re Griffith J. Griffith, [1896-1967]
  - Autobiography and biographical accounts, ca. 1903-1937. (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Crime and Criminals. Los Angeles: Prison Reform League, 1910., (Chapter 4 by Griffith) (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Griffith, Griffith J. Parks, Boulevards and Playgrounds. Los Angeles: Prison Reform League, 1910. (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and clippings, 1905-1950, including letter from Leo Tolstoy to Griffith, April 3/16, 1910. (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Ringbinder of research material compiled by Marion Bowen re Griffith and Rancho Los Feliz, 1937-1950. (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Legal documents re Griffith, including naturalization papers, 1877, copy will filed 1919, correspondence and papers re estate and gifts of property to the City of Los Angeles, 1896-1931. (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Articles and clippings re Griffith's park gifts, 1924-1967. (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence re Greek Theatre, 1913-1914. (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence re Hall of Science and Observatory, 1913-14. (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - 11 photographic prints. (Box 29)
  - 2 glass negatives of Griffith. (Box 29)
- Los Feliz Rancho History, [1845-1973]
  - Abstract of title, 1845-1887. (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous deeds and legal papers including abstract of title, schedule of deeds and field notes, 1871-1896. (Box 16, Folder 2-3)
  - Pictures and articles re 2 adobe buildings, ca. 1912-1921. (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - 2 framed pictures of adobe buildings. (Box 30)
  - Agreement to dig for treasure, 1896, and miscellaneous articles re history of the rancho, 1930-1973. (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Printed map of the Old Spanish and Mexican Ranchos of Los Angeles County. (Box 29)
- Griffith Park, [1917-1970s]
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, clippings and magazine articles, 1922-70s. (Box 17, Folder 1-4)
  - Clippings and correspondence re Park Commission and 1928 National Park Convention, 1917-1939. (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous articles re saving public parks, 1963-1975. (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Clippings and correspondence re Park Water System and fire protection, 1898-1957. (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, correspondence and papers re controversial decisions, 1916-1964. (Box 17, Folder 8-11)
  - Clippings re proposed projects not authorized, 1953-1963. (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, brochures, correspondence and miscellany re features of Griffith Park, 1931-1964. (Box 17, Folder 13-20)
  - 7 photographs of Griffith Park. (Box 17, Folder 21)
  - 6 Architect's drawings (Sketches 1-6) of proposed entrance to Mt. Hollywood Road, n.d. (Box 29)
- Greek Theatre, [1912-1975]
  - Correspondence, copy minutes, dedicatory program and miscellany, 1912-1962. (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1930-1975., (In envelope) (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, clippings and papers re development proposals, 1951-1969. (Box 18, Folder 3-4)
  - 2 photographic prints. (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Architect's sketch of Theatre. (Box 29)
- Hall of Science and Industry, [1912-1975]
  - Correspondence, copy minutes, reports and agreement and miscellaneous papers, 1912-1962. (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous pictures and sketches. (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Brochures and programs, ca. 1912-1955. (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1930s-1960s. (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Griffith Observer (February 1937-December 1975). (Box 19, Folder 5-7)
    vol.1, no.1-vol.39, no.12 (incomplete run).
  - Resolution by City Council on twentieth anniversary of Observatory, 1955. (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - 3 photographic negatives and 1 print. (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - 1 photographic print. (Box 30)
- Los Angeles Park System, [1891-1913]
  - Correspondence and clippings re park system and personalities, 1891-1970s. (Box 20, Folder 1-8)
  - 11 photographic prints of various parks. (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - 2 albums, photographs of various parks, 1911-1913. (Box 31)
- Van M. Griffith and Park Work, [1915-1923]
  - Clippings, photographs, record books and miscellany, 1915-1973. (Box 21, Folder 1-6)
  - Ledger, 1915-1923; printing block. (Box 21, Folder 1-6)
- Law Suits to Protect Griffith Park Property, [1946-1960]
  - Correspondence, legal papers and clippings, 1946-1960., (21 folders) (Box 22-24)
- Park Board, [September 1930-December 1931]
  - Copy minutes, September 1930-December 1931 (gaps)., (14 folders) (Box 25)
- Books and Reports Relating to Parks, [1969 and n.d.]
  - [No further description available]., (30 items) (Box 26)
  - Griffith park coster plan, 1969. (Box 31)
- Grand Jury Papers, [1934-1970s]
  - Manual for grand jurors in the City of New York. Grand Jury Association, New York County Fund Corporation, 1948. (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Reports of 1934 Los Angeles County Grand Jury. List of proposed grand jurors, 1934., (Bound volume) (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Final Report of 1936 Los Angeles County Grand Jury. (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - List of jurors, roster, notes of evidence, clippings, interim and final reports, 1949 Los Angeles County Grand Jury. (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Clippings and final report, 1951 Los Angeles County Grand Jury. (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Clippings and final report, 1952 Los Angeles County Grand Jury. (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, correspondence, various lists and miscellaneous items re County Grand juries, 1937-71, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 7-12)
  - Clippings and ephemera re the grand jury system, 1937-1971. (Box 27, Folder 13)
  - Photographic print of 1950 Grand Jury. (Box 30)
  - Correspondence, reports, clippings and papers re1950 County Grand Jury. (Box 28, Folder 1-6)
  - Correspondence, clippings and papers re1955 Federal Grand Jury. (Box 28, Folder 7)
- Miscellaneous Publications, [1912]
  - Sports{February 22, March 2, 1912). (Box 28, Folder 8)
    vol.1, no.1-2.
- Memorabilia and Miscellaneous, [1922-1955]
  - Resolution, Board of Park Commissioners to retiring Board President, 1930. (Box 30)
  - 2 certificates of appointment of Van M. Griffith as member of Board of Park Commissioners, 1922, 1927. (Box 30)
  - Plaque awarded to Van M Griffith as Foreman of the 1955 Federal Grand Jury of Southern California. (Box 30)
- Constance Griffith Papers, [1951-1953 and n.d.]
  - League of Women Voters study, Civil Liberty & Security (1952), Review of LWV Study & Action (1953). (Box 33)
  - Civil liberties studies approved, challenged, August 14 and 21, 1951. (Box 34)
  - Implementing the study of Civil Liberties & Security, 1951-1952. (Box 35)
  - Foundation of Freedoms Institute, March 1, 1952, Controversy over UNESCO (Box 36)
  - Foundation Freedom Institute and kit, controversy over UNESCO resignations, 1952-1953. (Box 37)
  - Constance Griffith letters, 1943-1949. (Box 38)
  - Silverlake unit. (Box 50)
  - Politics -- state & local goverment. (Box 51)
  - Personal papers. (Box 68)
  - University extension classes. (Box 97-99)
- [League of Women Voters, 1947-1963]
  - State & national, 1947-1960. (Box 40)
  - Los Angeles, 1947-1948. (Box 41)
  - 1948-1949. (Box 43)
  - 1949-1950. (Box 44)
  - 1950-1951. (Box 45)
  - Los Angeles, 1951-1952, mental health, miscellany -- civil liberties. (Box 46)
  - Los Angeles, 1954-1963. (Box 47)
  - Los Angeles, 1940-1953. (Box 48)
  - [No further description available]. (Box 53-58, 64-65)
  - Local government study. (Box 60, 63)
  - Local, 1941-1951. (Box 70-72)
  - League of Women Voters and local government study materials, 1944-1948, 1945-1951. (Box 80-82)
  - 1945-1951. (Box 83-85)
- [Miscellaneous, v.d.]
  - Van Griffith correspondence, papers, clippings. (Box 32)
  - Beverly Hills-Wilshire separation, 1941-1943. (Box 38)
  - Clippings re civil liberties, 1946-1953. (Box 39)
  - Education, housing, health, structure of goverment. (Box 48)
  - Silverlake, 1947-1951, community survey. (Box 49)
  - Removal of Van [Griffith] as police commissioner. (Box 52)
  - Clippings & articles on early aviation, 1920s-1930s. (Box 59)
  - Clippings & pamphlets about parks. (Box 61)
  - Unidentified. (Box 62)
  - Los Angeles county & city. (Box 67)
  - Citizens Research Institute -- seal & address cards. (Box 73)
  - Local government, 1952. (Box 74, 77)
  - Fundamentals of government. (Box 69, 75)
  - Unidentified [“1 letter from Norris Poulson”]. (Box 76)
  - Police Commission. (Box 66, 78-79, 95-96, 107-108)
  - Politics -- State & Local Government, 1947-1951. (Box 86-89)
    - Photograph of Griffith J. Griffith, printed material. (Box 86)
    - [No further description available]. (Box 87-88)
    - Publications. (Box 89)
  - Publications. (Box 91)
  - Citizens Research Institute. (Box 92-94, 100-104)
  - Parks, Griffith trust fund, elections. (Box 105-106)
  - Print blocks. (Box 109-117)
  - Articles of incorporation., (1 item) (Box 118)
Items Removed from Collection
64 glass negatives and 14 photographic negatives of aviators and aircraft [in small metal box].
[Items have not been placed in a box that can be requested. Consult Manuscripts Librarian for access.]